Oh, we're live.
오, 라이브입니다.
All right, yeah, we are live now.
네, 지금 생방송 중입니다.
Hey, everybody.
안녕, 여러분.
In the different platforms, we're actually
다른 플랫폼에서, 우리는 사실
broadcasting now with the help of our friends
친구들의 도움으로 지금 방송 중
from StreamYard to Twitch and YouTube and LinkedIn
스트림야드에서 트위치, 유튜브, 링크드인에 이르기까지
and what so I don't know.
그리고 나도 모르겠다.
So I hope that everybody can hear as well.
모두들 잘 들었으면 좋겠어요.
If not, just leave a comment or something.
안 들리면 댓글이나 뭐라도 남겨주세요.
We will see that and address that.
확인해서 해결하겠습니다.
So again, welcome.
다시 한 번 환영합니다.
I'm Andrei Binner from Aspecto.
아스펙토의 안드레이 비너입니다.
Michael here with me, my partner and co-founder.
제 파트너이자 공동 창업자인 마이클입니다.
You're probably here because you're
당신이 여기 있는 이유는 아마도
interested in open telemetry to some extent.
개방형 원격 측정에 어느 정도 관심이 있습니다.
And this is the purpose of this series.
이것이 이 시리즈의 목적입니다.
We're basically going to go over from the basics
기본부터 차근차근 살펴보겠습니다.
to the advanced stuff of open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리의 고급 기능에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
In the past two years, we've been working very extensively
지난 2년 동안 우리는 매우 광범위하게 작업해 왔습니다.
as part of our startup Aspecto on open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리에 대한 스타트업 Aspecto의 일환으로.
And actually, in the last couple of months,
그리고 실제로 지난 두 달 동안,
we learned that there is an increased
가 증가했다는 것을 알게 되었습니다.
interest in the industry.
업계에 대한 관심이 증가했습니다.
We meet more and more folks that would
점점 더 많은 사람들을 만납니다.
like to start using open telemetry,
개방형 텔레메트리를 사용하고 싶어하는 사람들을 더 많이 만나게 됩니다,
yeah, trying to get some tracing capabilities in your systems.
네, 시스템에서 추적 기능을 사용하려고 합니다.
And they don't have a lot of materials, a lot of help
자료도 별로 없고, 도움도 별로 없어요.
to get started.
시작하기 위해.
So I asked Michael, our expert in open telemetry,
그래서 오픈 텔레메트리 전문가인 마이클에게 물어봤습니다,
to do this series.
이 시리즈를 해달라고 부탁했습니다.
So we're going to start today with the first episode.
그럼 오늘부터 첫 번째 에피소드를 시작하겠습니다.
Although we are broadcasting it, feel free, again,
방송 중이지만, 다시 한 번 자유롭게 시청하세요,
to comment and ask questions.
댓글을 달고 질문할 수 있습니다.
We would like to make it as open discussion as we can.
최대한 열린 토론의 장을 만들고자 합니다.
So please be my guest.
그러니 마음껏 토론해 주세요.
And without further ado, Michael, to you.
더 이상 말할 것도 없이, 마이클, 당신을 위해.
OK, cool.
좋아, 멋지네.
So hello, everybody, and welcome to the Open Telemetry Bootcamp.
안녕하세요, 여러분, 오픈 텔레메트리 부트캠프에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Let me start sharing my screen.
화면 공유를 시작하겠습니다.
And we will go through what we have in this bootcamp, what
그리고 이 부트캠프에서 우리가 가지고 있는 것을 살펴볼 것입니다.
was the idea and the motivation to create the bootcamp, what
부트캠프를 만들게 된 아이디어와 동기는 무엇이었나요?
content you can expect.
기대할 수 있는 콘텐츠.
And just before jumping into the bootcamp itself,
그리고 부트캠프에 뛰어들기 직전,
I worried about myself.
내 자신에 대해 걱정했다.
So you will know why I'm speaking
내가 왜 말하는지 알겠지?
to you about those topics.
그 주제에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
So I've been working with microservices,
그래서 저는 마이크로서비스와 함께 일하고 있습니다,
the CIMU applications, for about five years now.
약 5년 동안 CIMU 애플리케이션을 개발해왔습니다.
Started as an independent consultant
독립 컨설턴트로 시작
and helped companies to migrate from monolith to microservices,
기업이 모놀리스에서 마이크로서비스로 마이그레이션하도록 지원했습니다,
helped company with too many services manage it,
너무 많은 서비스를 보유한 기업이 이를 관리하는 데 도움을 주었습니다,
also as an independent consultant and as an employee.
독립 컨설턴트로서 그리고 직원으로서도.
In the past two years, I founded a company
지난 2년 동안 회사를 설립했습니다.
around microservices and worked mostly with open telemetry.
마이크로 서비스 관련 회사를 설립했으며 주로 개방형 원격 측정으로 일했습니다.
So I gained some experience with open telemetry.
그래서 개방형 텔레메트리에 대한 경험을 쌓았습니다.
And I saw the difficulty people are having starting with it.
그리고 사람들이 시작하는 데 어려움을 겪는 것을 보았습니다.
And this is where the idea came to do a bootcamp.
그래서 부트캠프를 만들자는 아이디어가 떠올랐죠.
So our bootcamp is free and live,
그래서 부트캠프는 무료이며 라이브입니다,
mostly kind of starting with open telemetry.
대부분 오픈 텔레메트리로 시작합니다.
It would span over six sessions.
6개의 세션에 걸쳐 진행됩니다.
And it has nothing to do with the Spectre product.
스펙터 제품과는 아무런 관련이 없습니다.
We are not here to come and sell your product.
우리는 당신의 제품을 팔러 온 것이 아닙니다.
We're here to come and teach you open telemetry.
우리는 오픈 텔레메트리를 가르쳐 드리러 왔습니다.
We're definitely going to use the knowledge
우리는 확실히 지식을 사용할 것입니다.
that we gain while building Spectre,
스펙터를 만들면서 얻은 지식이죠,
but not to talk about the product itself.
제품 자체에 대한 이야기는 아닙니다.
So what can you expect from this bootcamp?
이 부트캠프에서 무엇을 기대할 수 있을까요?
So those are going to be the six main topics
6가지 주요 주제는 다음과 같습니다.
that we are going to cover.
우리가 다룰 주제입니다.
And I think those would be the one to get you confident
이걸로 자신감을 얻을 수 있을 것 같아요.
to deploy and manage open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리를 배포하고 관리할 수 있습니다.
So everything starts as developers and dev accessories
모든 것이 개발자와 개발 액세서리로 시작됩니다.
were responsible on the system that we build
우리가 구축하는 시스템에 대한 책임이 있습니다.
and open telemetry integrating to our system.
그리고 우리 시스템에 통합된 개방형 원격 측정.
So we need to understand how it works and what are the risks
따라서 우리는 그것이 어떻게 작동하고 어떤 위험이 있는지 이해해야 합니다.
and how things are operating internally.
그리고 내부적으로 어떻게 운영되는지 알아야 합니다.
So we are going to start by understanding how it works
먼저 어떻게 작동하는지 이해하는 것부터 시작하겠습니다.
and what's the motivation to the way that it's implemented.
그리고 그것이 구현되는 방식에 대한 동기가 무엇인지.
Once we understand how it's working,
어떻게 작동하는지 이해했다면,
we can then try and integrate it to an application.
애플리케이션에 통합할 수 있습니다.
We will go and make the necessary code changes
이제 필요한 코드를 변경하겠습니다.
in order to have open telemetry,
오픈 텔레메트리를 위해,
open telemetry collects data and then ships it somewhere.
개방형 텔레메트리는 데이터를 수집한 다음 어딘가로 전송합니다.
So that will be the second phase.
이것이 두 번째 단계입니다.
Once we have started to collect data
데이터 수집이 시작되면
and this data needs to be shipped somewhere.
이 데이터를 어딘가로 전송해야 합니다.
So for that, we're going to deploy
이를 위해, 우리는 다음을 배포할 것입니다.
all kinds of backend components
모든 종류의 백엔드 컴포넌트
that are going to receive the data and process it,
데이터를 수신하고 처리할 컴포넌트들,
ingest it, analyze it, visualize it.
수집하고, 분석하고, 시각화합니다.
And for that, I'll refer to it as the open telemetry stack.
이를 위해 오픈 텔레메트리 스택이라고 부르겠습니다.
And when that's deployed,
그리고 그것이 배포되면,
it's going to production environment.
프로덕션 환경으로 이동합니다.
This is where the fun begins
재미가 시작되는 곳
and we're trying to get a lot of traffic and a lot of data.
우리는 많은 트래픽과 많은 데이터를 얻으려고 노력하고 있습니다.
And then we need to start to manage it under high scale.
그리고 나서 대규모로 관리하기 시작해야 합니다.
We will learn how to do it,
방법을 배웁니다,
both in terms of the infrastructure,
둘 다 인프라 측면에서,
auto-scaling and those kinds of things,
자동 확장 및 그런 종류의 것들,
but most importantly, from the open telemetry perspective,
하지만 가장 중요한 것은 개방형 원격 측정의 관점입니다,
how we're efficient with the data that we're collecting,
우리가 수집하는 데이터를 어떻게 효율적으로 사용할 수 있는지입니다,
how we're collecting the right amount of data
적절한 양의 데이터를 수집하는 방법
and not too much data.
너무 많은 데이터를 수집하지 않는 방법
The fifth part, so your application may be similar
다섯 번째 부분이므로 애플리케이션도 비슷할 수 있습니다.
to other application, but it's not the same.
다른 애플리케이션과 비슷하지만 동일하지는 않습니다.
And you definitely will need to do some customization
그리고 약간의 사용자 정의가 필요합니다.
to open telemetry, usually very few,
텔레메트리를 열려면, 보통은 거의 없습니다,
but you need to understand how to do it.
하지만 어떻게 하는지 이해해야 합니다.
And last thing would be,
그리고 마지막으로
we did a lot of work to have open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리를 위해 많은 노력을 기울였습니다.
and to collect this data.
이 데이터를 수집하기 위해 많은 노력을 기울였습니다.
Let's make sure that we're squeezing the lemon
레몬을 잘 짜고 있는지 확인해 봅시다.
and we're getting the most out of our open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리를 최대한 활용하고 있습니다.
So those are going to be the topics
따라서 다음과 같은 주제가 될 것입니다.
that we're going to cover.
우리가 다룰 주제입니다.
This is the process that I want you to go with us.
이 과정을 함께 해주시길 바랍니다.
So I hope you find it interesting.
재미있게 보셨으면 좋겠어요.
And if you feel there is something missing,
그리고 뭔가 빠진 게 있다면,
please reach out and let us know.
로 연락하여 알려주세요.
So we're going to have three main sections.
세 가지 주요 섹션으로 구성됩니다.
The first one will be mostly around coding
첫 번째 섹션은 주로 코딩에 관한 것입니다.
and making changes to application.
그리고 애플리케이션을 변경하는 것입니다.
The second one will be mostly about deployment
두 번째는 주로 배포에 관한 것입니다.
and configuring it for high scale.
그리고 대규모로 구성하는 것입니다.
And the last section will be about
그리고 마지막 섹션은
customizing open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리 사용자 지정.
This bootcamp, we decided to do it with live coding
이번 부트캠프에서는 라이브 코딩으로 진행하기로 결정했습니다.
and live demo.
그리고 라이브 데모.
It's going to be quite an hands-on thing.
꽤나 실습이 될 겁니다.
The first session today is going to be a bit more talking
오늘 첫 번째 세션은 좀 더 많은 이야기를 나눌 예정입니다.
and less coding, but overall live code, live demos.
코딩보다는 전반적인 라이브 코드와 라이브 데모로 진행됩니다.
We want it to be hands-on.
우리는 실습을 원합니다.
We want you to learn from experience.
우리는 경험을 통해 배우기를 원합니다.
That means that when you do live code and live demo,
즉, 라이브 코딩과 라이브 데모를 할 때입니다,
things may not work, but this is a great chance
가 작동하지 않을 수도 있지만, 이것은 좋은 기회입니다.
to understand why they are not working
왜 작동하지 않는지 이해하기 위해
and to see for firsthand how the debugging
그리고 디버깅이 어떻게 작동하는지 직접 확인하기 위해
and troubleshoot process looks like.
및 문제 해결 과정이 어떻게 진행되는지 직접 확인할 수 있습니다.
We do have a few resources available for you.
사용 가능한 몇 가지 리소스가 있습니다.
So we have a GitHub repo where you can find the code,
코드를 찾을 수 있는 GitHub 리포지토리가 있습니다,
the presentation, more resources to read.
프레젠테이션, 더 많은 리소스를 읽을 수 있습니다.
So if you want that, you can check it out.
원하시면 확인해보세요.
And also we having a Slack channel under the CNCF worksite.
그리고 CNCF 워크사이트 아래에 Slack 채널도 있습니다.
It's a great space where you can just communicate with us.
저희와 소통할 수 있는 훌륭한 공간입니다.
So again, it's live, use it, ask question.
다시 한 번 말씀드리지만, 라이브이니 이용하고 질문하세요.
And I think that's about it to tell you
여기까지만 말씀드리겠습니다.
about what is the open telemetry bootcamp.
오픈 텔레메트리 부트캠프가 뭔지 알려드릴게요.
And we can dive right into the first episode
이제 첫 번째 에피소드로 바로 들어가 보겠습니다.
where we're going to talk about the architecture,
건축에 대해 이야기하겠습니다,
the motivation of open telemetry
개방형 원격 측정의 동기
and see the first project of open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리의 첫 번째 프로젝트 보기
that we're going to work on.
우리가 작업할 프로젝트입니다.
So before I'm starting to give you the typical lecture
일반적인 강의를 시작하기 전에 먼저
of what is open telemetry, why should you use it,
오픈 텔레메트리가 무엇인지, 왜 사용해야 하는지 설명하겠습니다,
let's take it from an example.
예를 들어 보겠습니다.
Let's take a real example that we can all relate to
우리 모두가 공감할 수 있는 실제 예를 들어 보겠습니다.
and try to figure out how we were working
우리가 어떻게 작업했는지 알아봅시다.
with this example with and without open telemetry.
이 예제는 오픈 텔레메트리를 사용했을 때와 사용하지 않았을 때를 비교합니다.
And my example would be something very common.
그리고 제 예제는 매우 일반적인 예제입니다.
So you would get an alert.
그래서 경고를 받게 됩니다.
You get an alert that some service,
어떤 서비스에 대한 경고를 받습니다,
service A is not able to write data to DB1.
서비스 A가 DB1에 데이터를 쓸 수 없습니다.
That is a scary alert.
무서운 경고입니다.
That means that some service is not working.
일부 서비스가 작동하지 않는다는 뜻입니다.
They are not doing what they're supposed to do.
서비스가 제대로 작동하지 않습니다.
They're not able to write data.
데이터를 쓸 수 없습니다.
Maybe we're even at a data loss situation.
데이터 손실 상황일 수도 있습니다.
This is something that we need to put our mind into.
이것은 우리가 마음을 써야 할 부분입니다.
We need to fix it.
고쳐야겠어.
We need to act fast and down times and bugs
다운타임과 버그에 빠르게 대처해야 합니다.
and critical issues are bound to happen.
중요한 문제가 발생하기 마련입니다.
The question is how fast can you fix it?
문제는 얼마나 빨리 고칠 수 있느냐입니다.
How accurate you are in your fix?
얼마나 정확하게 고치나요?
And this is what we wanna do.
이것이 우리가 하고 싶은 일입니다.
So try to think for a second.
그러니 잠시만 생각해보세요.
You got an alert from your log solution saying
로그 솔루션에서 다음과 같은 경고를 받았습니다.
service A can't write to DB1.
서비스 A가 DB1에 쓸 수 없습니다.
What are your first instincts?
당신의 첫 번째 본능은 무엇인가요?
What the first thing that you're going to do?
가장 먼저 할 일은 무엇인가요?
What are the tools that you're going to open?
어떤 도구를 열려고 하나요?
What are the questions that you're going,
어떤 질문을 하려고 하나요?
that are going to run in your head when you're fixing it?
고칠 때 머릿속에 떠오르는 질문이 있나요?
I can think of a few.
몇 개 생각나는데요.
I can think of, okay, I know service A
알겠어요, 서비스 A를 알아요.
is sending some exceptions.
일부 예외를 보내고 있습니다.
I can locate this exception in my code
내 코드에서 이 예외를 찾을 수 있습니다.
and then I can track the flow in my flow,
내 흐름에서 흐름을 추적할 수 있습니다,
in my code that led to this exception.
이 예외를 발생시킨 코드에서.
Maybe it will give me some hints.
힌트를 얻을 수 있을지도 모르겠네요.
Maybe this service was recently deployed
이 서비스가 최근에 배포된 것일 수 있습니다.
and that's the issue.
그게 문제입니다.
And maybe there are some database metrics
그리고 데이터베이스 메트릭이 있을 수도 있습니다.
that I want to check out.
확인하고 싶어요.
Maybe that's the reason DB1 is not available at all.
아마도 이것이 DB1을 전혀 사용할 수 없는 이유일 것입니다.
So I would start with those.
그래서 저는 그것부터 시작하겠습니다.
I guess you guys may have other things
다른 것도 있을 것 같네요
that you can think of.
생각나는 게 있겠지.
So let's say that the logs show an exception.
로그에 예외가 있다고 가정해 봅시다.
You follow the code.
코드를 따라갑니다.
You don't find anything too interesting.
별로 흥미로운 것을 찾지 못했습니다.
When you look at the metrics of DB1,
DB1의 메트릭을 살펴보면 다음과 같습니다,
you do see high CPU, which is interesting.
CPU가 높은 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
It's something new that has changed.
뭔가 새로운 것이 변경되었습니다.
And then I would ask a fairly simple question.
그리고 아주 간단한 질문을 하죠.
Maybe we're just having more traffic
트래픽이 더 많은 것일 수도 있습니다.
and it's not really a problem.
별 문제도 아니야.
Well, it is a problem, but more traffic,
음, 문제이긴 하지만 트래픽이 더 많습니다,
it's probably a good thing.
아마 좋은 일이겠지.
So maybe we need to look at traffic.
트래픽을 살펴봐야 할 것 같습니다.
And then to ask myself,
그리고 스스로에게 물어봅니다,
which HTTP route are causing to service A to write in DB1?
어떤 HTTP 경로가 서비스 A로 하여금 DB1에 쓰게 만들었을까요?
That's a fairly question.
꽤 괜찮은 질문입니다.
I may not know that question from the top of my head.
그 질문은 제가 잘 모르겠는데요.
Maybe I need to check it out.
확인해 봐야겠어.
And maybe my assumption that it's an HTTP is wrong.
HTTP라는 내 가정이 틀렸을 수도 있겠군.
Maybe it's because service A consumes some Kafka messages
서비스 A가 일부 카프카 메시지를 소비하기 때문일 수도 있습니다.
and then in response to that, write to the database.
그리고 그에 대한 응답으로 데이터베이스에 씁니다.
So this is the thought process that I would go through.
이것이 제가 생각하는 사고 과정입니다.
And if I'm looking at this diagram
이 다이어그램을 보면 다음과 같습니다.
of the overall service architecture,
전체 서비스 아키텍처의
so I have here service A,
그래서 여기 서비스 A가 있습니다,
and service A is writing to DB1.
그리고 서비스 A는 DB1에 쓰고 있습니다.
And if I need to know who is calling service A,
그리고 누가 서비스 A를 호출하는지 알고 싶습니다,
whether it's the front end or some, I don't know,
프런트 엔드인지 뭔지 모르겠어요,
mobile device or other services, it's hard for me to know.
모바일 기기나 다른 서비스인지 잘 모르겠습니다.
Thinking about metrics and logs,
메트릭과 로그에 대해 생각 중입니다,
it's even more complicated to know who called service A.
누가 서비스 A를 호출했는지 아는 것은 훨씬 더 복잡합니다.
And there are tools that may help you,
도움이 될 수 있는 도구가 있습니다,
some tools that can't help you,
도움이 되지 않는 도구도 있습니다,
but let's say that you know from the top of your head again,
하지만 다시 머리로만 알고 있다고 가정해 봅시다,
that both service B and service C are calling service A.
서비스 B와 서비스 C가 모두 서비스 A를 호출하고 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
Okay, so now we have two consumer for service A.
이제 서비스 A에 대한 두 명의 소비자가 생겼습니다.
And now the question is which one of them
이제 문제는 다음 중 어느 것이
is calling service A that is actually producing the error
가 실제로 오류를 발생시키는 서비스 A를 호출하고 있는가이다.
that we're experiencing?
우리가 겪고 있는 오류는?
Is it service C, is it service B, or maybe it's just both?
서비스 C인가요, 서비스 B인가요, 아니면 둘 다인가요?
So this is something that now,
이게 바로 지금입니다,
if I'm thinking again about logs and metrics,
로그와 메트릭에 대해 다시 생각해보자,
it's kind of hard to answer this question.
이 질문에 답하기가 좀 어렵네요.
And this is where we're maybe unveiling the third
그리고 여기서 우리는 아마도 세 번째를 공개할 것입니다.
and important part of open telemetry, which is a trace.
개방형 텔레메트리의 중요한 부분인 추적입니다.
So let's start with the log.
그럼 로그부터 시작하겠습니다.
We all know what logs are,
우리 모두 로그가 무엇인지 알고 있습니다,
basically a message that telling you
기본적으로 다음을 알려주는 메시지입니다.
something doesn't work and we know metric.
무언가 작동하지 않으며 메트릭을 알고 있습니다.
We have some number representing some value in the system.
시스템에서 어떤 값을 나타내는 숫자가 있습니다.
And then we have a trace.
그리고 추적이 있습니다.
And the trace is going to tell us the context.
이 추적을 통해 컨텍스트를 알 수 있습니다.
It's going to tell us the path that a specific API
특정 API가 호출한 경로를 알려줍니다.
or a specific backend interaction, what path it took,
또는 특정 백엔드 상호 작용이 어떤 경로를 거쳤는지 알려줍니다,
which services it visited before it hit that error.
해당 오류가 발생하기 전에 어떤 서비스를 방문했는지.
This kind of the same way that you would try to look
이와 같은 방식으로 다음과 같이 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
at the call stack and see that a specific invocation
호출 스택을 살펴보고 특정 호출이
jumped from function to function.
함수에서 함수로 이동했습니다.
I wanna know from each service to service it jumped.
각 서비스에서 서비스로 점프했는지 알고 싶습니다.
Once I understand and I can visualize,
이해가 되고 시각화할 수 있게 되면
I can see that maybe all of the issues that I had
제가 가지고 있던 모든 문제들이
are related to service B,
서비스 B와 관련이 있습니다,
this is a very important piece of information for me
이것은 저에게 매우 중요한 정보입니다.
to resolve the issue and to resolve it fast.
문제를 해결하고 빠르게 해결할 수 있습니다.
Because now I know that I need to look
이제 저는
whether the increases traffic is related to service B,
트래픽 증가가 서비스 B와 관련이 있는지 확인해야 합니다,
or if I know that it's specific to service B,
또는 서비스 B와 관련된 것인지 알 수 있습니다,
maybe deployment in service B is the one
아마도 서비스 B에 배포하는 것이
that caused the issues in service A.
서비스 A에서 문제를 일으켰을 수 있습니다.
So basically when we get more data points
따라서 기본적으로 더 많은 데이터 포인트를 얻으면
describing the whole story, it starts to get easier.
전체 스토리를 설명하는 것이 더 쉬워지기 시작합니다.
So to resolve this issue fast,
이 문제를 빨리 해결하려면,
I needed to have all three of logs, metrics and end traces.
로그, 메트릭, 엔드 트레이스 세 가지가 모두 필요했습니다.
And I've said traces quite a few times.
트레이스라고 여러 번 말씀드렸습니다.
So let me give you a visualization of a trace.
그럼 트레이스를 시각화해서 보여드리겠습니다.
So here you can see a UI that displays a trace,
트레이스를 표시하는 UI를 볼 수 있습니다,
specifically Eager UI.
특히 Eager UI입니다.
And what you can see here,
그리고 여기서 볼 수 있는 것들,
you can see that we have older service,
이전 서비스임을 알 수 있습니다,
it got an API call to slash purchase slash order.
구매 슬래시 주문을 슬래시하는 API 호출을 받았습니다.
The whole thing took a bit over two seconds.
전체적으로 2초가 조금 넘게 걸렸습니다.
And older service, the first thing that it did,
그리고 이전 서비스에서 가장 먼저 한 일입니다,
it communicated with user service to verify the user.
사용자 서비스와 통신하여 사용자를 확인했습니다.
That's great.
잘됐네요.
And once that's done, I can see that older service
완료되면 이전 서비스를 볼 수 있습니다.
communicated with stock service and asked to update the stock.
재고 서비스와 통신하여 재고를 업데이트하도록 요청했습니다.
And eventually the stock service ran a Mongoose query,
결국 주식 서비스가 몽구스 쿼리를 실행했습니다,
which is a MongoDB library to update many of the stock items.
몽구스 쿼리를 실행하여 많은 재고 항목을 업데이트했습니다.
Only when that's done,
완료된 경우에만,
we published a new older Kafka message.
새로운 이전 카프카 메시지를 게시했습니다.
So basically I told you a story.
그래서 기본적으로 나는 당신에게 이야기를 들려줬어요.
I told you a story of how a particular API
특정 API가 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 이야기를 했죠.
rolled through the different services.
다른 서비스를 통해 전달되는 과정을 설명했습니다.
And I was able to do it, not only to tell you
그리고 저는 해낼 수 있었습니다.
which services it visited,
어떤 서비스를 방문했는지도요,
also whether they were happening in sequence or in parallel.
또한 순차적으로 발생했는지 또는 병렬로 발생했는지 여부도 확인합니다.
And I am able to tell you this whole story
그리고 나는 이 모든 이야기를 당신에게 말할 수 있습니다.
and it's kind of a data tree, a tree structure
일종의 데이터 트리, 트리 구조입니다.
where we can see what was the root
어디가 루트인지 알 수 있습니다.
and what happened because of a root.
그리고 루트로 인해 어떤 일이 일어났는지 알 수 있습니다.
So now we are a bit smother with what traces are.
이제 흔적이 무엇인지 조금은 알 것 같습니다.
So we're talking about those three things altogether.
그래서 우리는 이 세 가지에 대해 함께 이야기하고 있습니다.
We're talking about the logs.
로그에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
Basically the application itself is telling us a story.
기본적으로 애플리케이션 자체가 우리에게 이야기를 들려주고 있습니다.
It outputs some messages that we can read as humans
인간으로서 읽을 수 있는 몇 가지 메시지를 출력합니다.
and understand what went in that particular application.
특정 애플리케이션에 무엇이 들어갔는지 이해할 수 있습니다.
The metric tells the statistical data about our system.
이 메트릭은 시스템에 대한 통계 데이터를 알려줍니다.
How it was the CPU, how many API code did I get?
CPU는 어땠고, API 코드는 몇 개였나요?
And traces are the context and the story and the path
그리고 흔적은 맥락과 스토리, 경로입니다.
that each event took.
각 사건이 걸어온 길입니다.
Those three would usually be referred
이 세 가지는 보통 다음과 같이 참조됩니다.
to the three pillar of observability.
가 관찰 가능성의 세 가지 기둥으로 참조됩니다.
So observability is a new term, a new trend,
가관측성은 새로운 용어이자 새로운 트렌드입니다,
basically trying to say how we should do monitoring
기본적으로 모니터링을 어떻게 해야 하는지를 말하려고 합니다.
in distributed cloud native application.
분산된 클라우드 네이티브 애플리케이션에서.
And if we were today was using logs and metrics and APM,
오늘 로그와 메트릭, APM을 사용했다면요,
with distributed application, it's not enough usually
분산 애플리케이션에서는 일반적으로 충분하지 않습니다.
and this is why we're starting to see
그리고 이것이 우리가 보기 시작한 이유입니다.
the rise of observability,
관측 가능성의 부상
which essentially it's those three things.
본질적으로 이 세 가지입니다.
It's logs, it's metrics and traces altogether.
로그, 메트릭, 그리고 추적입니다.
So what is open telemetry?
그렇다면 개방형 텔레메트리란 무엇인가요?
Why I said this is the open telemetry bootcamp,
오픈 텔레메트리 부트캠프라고 말한 이유,
but I didn't mention open telemetry in the past few minutes.
지난 몇 분 동안 오픈 텔레메트리에 대해 언급하지 않았어요.
So open telemetry in some way is the three pillars.
어떤 식으로든 개방형 텔레메트리는 세 가지 기둥입니다.
Open telemetry is the ability to collect logs, metrics
개방형 텔레메트리는 로그, 메트릭을 수집하는 기능입니다.
and traces and you can argue and say,
추적할 수 있는 기능입니다,
hey, I'm collecting logs today.
안녕, 나 오늘 로그 수집 중이야.
Right now as you speak, I have logs and metrics.
지금 이 순간에도 로그와 메트릭을 수집하고 있습니다.
I just need traces so I can just use open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리를 사용할 수 있도록 추적만 필요합니다.
and collect the traces from open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리에서 트레이스를 수집합니다.
But the magic really happens
하지만 마법은 실제로 일어납니다.
where they are all correlated altogether.
모두 상관관계가 있는 곳입니다.
And the traces are attached to the logs
그리고 추적은 로그에 첨부됩니다.
and the log attached to the trace says,
추적에 첨부된 로그는 다음과 같습니다,
and everything is glued together,
그리고 모든 것이 서로 붙어 있습니다,
making it that when you need to resolve some issue,
어떤 문제를 해결해야 할 때 그렇게 만들 수 있습니다,
moving from logs to traces, from traces to metrics
로그에서 트레이스, 트레이스에서 메트릭으로 이동합니다.
is fast and very efficient.
는 빠르고 매우 효율적입니다.
So open telemetry for me is the glue.
그래서 저에게 오픈 텔레메트리는 접착제입니다.
Open telemetry is basically the ability to collect
개방형 텔레메트리는 기본적으로 데이터를 수집하는 기능입니다.
all three pillars under one unified SDK.
세 가지 기둥을 모두 하나의 통합 SDK로 통합하는 것입니다.
So open telemetry is a big part of it is the SDK.
따라서 개방형 텔레메트리의 가장 큰 부분은 SDK입니다.
There are a bit more paths that we will see in a second,
잠시 후 더 많은 경로를 볼 수 있습니다,
but open telemetry is a project under CNCF.
하지만 오픈 텔레메트리는 CNCF의 프로젝트입니다.
CNCF is the Cloud Native Compute Foundation.
CNCF는 클라우드 네이티브 컴퓨팅 재단입니다.
They're responsible for Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스를 담당하고 있습니다.
So open telemetry is in a good hand.
그래서 개방형 원격 분석은 좋은 손에 있습니다.
And basically, if you look at the project structure,
그리고 기본적으로 프로젝트 구조를 살펴보면,
at least the main part of it is you have one specification
적어도 주요한 부분은 하나의 사양이 있다는 것입니다.
how data should be collected and should be sent.
데이터를 어떻게 수집하고 전송해야 하는지.
And then you have implementation
그리고 구현이 있습니다.
through different programming languages.
을 다른 프로그래밍 언어로 구현합니다.
Because it is an SDK, we need to support
SDK이므로 다음을 지원해야 합니다.
all kinds of different programming languages.
모든 종류의 다른 프로그래밍 언어를 지원해야 합니다.
Of course, the modern one are supported like Node,
물론 노드와 같은 최신 언어도 지원됩니다,
Java, Python, Go, Ruby.
자바, 파이썬, 고, 루비.
Any modern one would be probably supported.
모든 최신 언어가 지원될 것입니다.
So in a very short explanation,
아주 짧게 설명하자면
open telemetry is the three pillars glued together
개방형 원격 측정은 세 개의 기둥이 서로 붙어 있습니다.
as an SDK under the CNCF with one specification
하나의 사양으로 CNCF에 따라 SDK로 제공됩니다.
so they could communicate with one another.
서로 통신할 수 있도록 했습니다.
Okay, cool.
좋아, 멋지네.
So now that we have a bit of a sense
이제 어느 정도 감이 오네요.
what open telemetry is, we need to talk about how it works.
개방형 텔레메트리가 무엇인지, 어떻게 작동하는지에 대해 이야기할 필요가 있습니다.
And I'm going to do it in three sections.
세 부분으로 나눠서 설명할게요.
The first one would be to describe
첫 번째는
what is the open telemetry stack,
오픈 텔레메트리 스택이란 무엇인가요?
what you need to deploy in order to have
다음을 갖기 위해 배포해야 하는 것
open telemetry up and running.
오픈 텔레메트리를 실행합니다.
Then we're going to take a deeper dive
이제 더 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
into how the open telemetry SDK,
오픈 텔레메트리 SDK가 어떻게 작동하는지 살펴보겠습니다,
the portion that you implement in your code,
코드에서 구현하는 부분입니다,
how does it work?
어떻게 작동하나요?
And then we're going to do a live demo
그리고 라이브 데모를 해보겠습니다.
and show you a real application collecting logs,
로그를 수집하는 실제 애플리케이션을 보여드리겠습니다,
collecting metrics, collecting traces,
메트릭을 수집하고, 트레이스를 수집합니다,
and give you a sense of how it looks like.
어떻게 생겼는지 알 수 있습니다.
Okay, so we said that open telemetry is an SDK
자, 오픈 텔레메트리는 SDK라고 말씀드렸습니다.
and collects all three pillars.
세 개의 기둥을 모두 수집합니다.
That's great.
대단하네요.
That means that it's done in memory, in process.
메모리에서 처리 중이라는 뜻입니다.
So we're going to have some backend
그래서 우리는 백엔드에서
that is going to ingest the traces, logs,
트레이스와 로그를 수집할 백엔드가 있습니다,
and metrics that we just received.
그리고 방금 받은 메트릭을 수집합니다.
And then to store it in a database.
그리고 이를 데이터베이스에 저장합니다.
That's cool.
멋지네요.
And once we have something in the database,
일단 데이터베이스에 뭔가가 있으면
we need to query and to visualize it.
쿼리하고 시각화해야 합니다.
And that would be our last layer.
이것이 우리의 마지막 레이어가 될 것입니다.
So mostly we're talking about three layers.
그래서 대부분 세 개의 레이어에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
So how does it look for more a diagram perspective?
다이어그램 관점에서 보면 어떻게 보일까요?
So at the top, we have three microservices.
맨 위에는 3개의 마이크로서비스가 있습니다.
All of them install open telemetry.
모두 개방형 텔레메트리를 설치합니다.
So they're collecting logs, events, metrics.
그래서 로그, 이벤트, 메트릭을 수집하고 있습니다.
When those are being collected,
그것들이 수집되고 있을 때,
they are being exported to an open telemetry collector.
개방형 텔레메트리 수집기로 내보내고 있습니다.
Open telemetry collector is a backend
개방형 텔레메트리 수집기가 백엔드입니다.
that can ingest these telemetry data.
텔레메트리 데이터를 수집할 수 있는 백엔드입니다.
And it can process it.
그리고 처리할 수 있습니다.
It can process it and do all kinds of things
처리하고 모든 종류의 일을 할 수 있습니다.
that we will deep dive into later this course.
이 강좌의 뒷부분에서 자세히 살펴볼 것입니다.
And once it receives those messages
그리고 이 메시지를 받으면
and this telemetry data, it's going to be shipped somewhere.
그리고 이 원격 측정 데이터는 어딘가로 전송될 것입니다.
Usually a database may be a message broker
일반적으로 데이터베이스는 메시지 브로커일 수 있습니다.
and then a database,
그리고 데이터베이스,
but at the end of the day,
하지만 하루가 끝나면
it's going to be stored in a database.
데이터베이스에 저장됩니다.
And once we have everything stored,
모든 것이 저장되면
we need to visualize this data.
이 데이터를 시각화해야 합니다.
And this is where we're going to use,
여기가 우리가 사용할 곳입니다,
at this course, we're going to use an open source
이 강좌에서는 오픈 소스를 사용하겠습니다.
and we're going to use Yeager.
예거를 사용하겠습니다.
Of course, there is an endless amount of vendors
물론 벤더는 무궁무진합니다.
that knows how to work with this data as well.
이 데이터로 작업하는 방법도 알고 있습니다.
So if you are going to start open telemetry tomorrow,
따라서 내일 오픈 텔레메트리를 시작하려면,
you start by implementing in your code,
을 코드에 구현하는 것부터 시작해야 합니다,
then send it somewhere that is going to get this data,
를 구현한 다음 이 데이터를 가져올 곳으로 전송합니다,
store it and visualize it.
저장하고 시각화합니다.
Okay, that's cool.
좋아요, 멋지네요.
We can proceed to the next phase.
다음 단계로 넘어가도 됩니다.
And the next phase is after we know what is the stack,
다음 단계는 스택이 무엇인지 파악한 후입니다,
we can proceed to deep dive into the SDK itself
SDK 자체에 대한 심층 분석을 진행할 수 있습니다.
and understand how it work.
어떻게 작동하는지 이해할 수 있습니다.
I mentioned four layers.
네 개의 레이어를 언급했습니다.
I will say that when we progress in this course,
이 과정을 진행하면서 말씀드리겠습니다,
we would see that we can reduce the amount of layers
레이어의 양을 줄일 수 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
or add some layers to simplify stuff
또는 일부 레이어를 추가하여 단순화할 수 있습니다.
or to make it more complex.
또는 더 복잡하게 만들 수 있습니다.
But in a nutshell, and at this phase of the course,
하지만 간단히 말해서, 이 단계에서는,
let's address this as four layers.
네 개의 레이어로 표현해 봅시다.
Okay, so you took the first step
자, 첫 번째 단계를 수행했습니다.
and you took some service,
그리고 서비스를 받았군요,
a victim service in your application
애플리케이션의 피해자 서비스
that you're going to try and implement open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리를 구현하려고 합니다.
Cool, so let's say that this is an example
좋아요, 그럼 이것이 예시라고 가정해 봅시다.
of an architecture with a front end communicating
프론트 엔드와 통신하는 아키텍처의
with service A that communicates with service B
서비스 A와 통신하는 서비스 B
that eventually write data to a database.
결국 데이터베이스에 데이터를 씁니다.
Both service A and service B
서비스 A와 서비스 B 모두
have open telemetry installed in them.
에 개방형 텔레메트리가 설치되어 있습니다.
Now, when we are trying to think how a trace looks,
이제 트레이스가 어떻게 생겼는지 생각해 보겠습니다,
if you remember, we had the purchase service,
기억하시겠지만, 구매 서비스가 있었죠,
the auto service communicating with the user service.
사용자 서비스와 통신하는 자동 서비스입니다.
And I told you that it's kind of a tree view.
일종의 트리뷰라고 말씀드렸잖아요.
In order to have a tree view,
트리 뷰를 가지려면,
we need to have a parent and child relation.
부모와 자식 관계가 있어야 합니다.
That means that any data that would be sent from service B
즉, 서비스 B에서 전송되는 모든 데이터는
it needs to be under the context
컨텍스트 아래에 있어야 합니다.
as a child of what happened in service A.
서비스 A에서 일어난 일의 자식으로.
For that reason, when service A is sending an API call
따라서 서비스 A가 API 호출을 보낼 때
to service B, it's going to inject some headers
을 서비스 B로 보낼 때, 일부 헤더를 삽입합니다.
in the HTTP headers.
헤더를 삽입합니다.
And that would help us to understand
그러면 다음과 같이 이해하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
that who has service B to understand who is the parent,
누가 부모인지 이해하기 위해 누가 서비스 B를 가지고 있는지,
what is the cause, what led up to this API call
원인이 무엇인지, 이 API 호출에 이르게 된 원인
so we would know that service B is the child service A
그래서 서비스 B가 자식 서비스 A라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
in this particular case.
이 특별한 경우에는
And then the open telemetry is going to send data
그리고 개방형 텔레메트리가 데이터를 전송합니다.
to our collector and is going to say,
를 수집기로 보내고 다음과 같이 말할 것입니다,
hey, collector, please, you should know
이봐요, 수집가, 제발, 당신은 알아야 해요.
that I sent an API call to service B.
서비스 B에 API 호출을 보냈습니다.
And this is all done under trace ID, number one,
그리고 이 모든 것이 추적 ID 1번에서 이루어집니다,
because we want to know how to find this trace later on.
나중에 이 추적을 찾는 방법을 알고 싶기 때문입니다.
And then service B is going to say,
그리고 서비스 B는 다음과 같이 말할 것입니다,
hey, I got an API call from service A
안녕하세요, 서비스 A에서 API 호출을 받았습니다.
and now I do have a parent.
이제 부모가 생겼어요.
Now this thing, it has a parent and the parent is service A.
이제 이것은 부모가 있고 부모는 서비스 A입니다.
So in this case, now any data that would be sent
따라서 이 경우 이제 전송되는 모든 데이터는
from service B, it would have a parent.
로 전송되는 데이터는 부모를 갖게 됩니다.
Then of course we have service B sending again this data
그러면 당연히 서비스 B가 이 데이터를 다시 전송합니다.
to send data about the DB query.
로 DB 쿼리에 대한 데이터를 전송합니다.
Of course it has service A as its parent and that's,
물론 서비스 A를 부모로 두고 있습니다,
so service A is the parent.
따라서 서비스 A가 부모입니다.
Service A is its parent and that's, so goes later on.
서비스 A가 부모이므로 이후에도 마찬가지입니다.
I can do the same kind of visualization,
같은 종류의 시각화를 할 수 있습니다,
but I would add an additional data about it
하지만 이에 대한 추가 데이터를 추가합니다.
at every interaction that we have.
모든 상호작용에서.
So when service A is sending an API call,
따라서 서비스 A가 API 호출을 보낼 때,
that refers to spam, a single event within the trace.
는 스팸을 가리키며, 추적 내 단일 이벤트입니다.
And the span is of course, it spans over time.
그리고 그 범위는 당연히 시간에 걸쳐 있습니다.
It has a start point and a duration
시작점과 지속 시간이 있습니다.
and that being an end time.
그리고 종료 시간입니다.
And you can see that the first span has no parent
그리고 첫 번째 스팬에는 부모가 없음을 알 수 있습니다.
because it's the first one, it's the root one.
첫 번째 스팬이 루트 스팬이기 때문입니다.
And the span ID is 55.
그리고 스팬 ID는 55입니다.
And when we're looking at this span,
그리고 이 스팬을 보면,
when this span ID is 66, it does has a parent,
이 스팬 ID가 66이면 부모가 있습니다,
even though I made a mistake, it has a parent
내가 실수했지만, 부모가 있다.
and the parent is 55.
부모는 55세입니다.
And this is how we're able to construct
이렇게 하면 다음과 같이 구성할 수 있습니다.
the structure of the trace.
트레이스의 구조입니다.
Okay, so I talked quite a lot in theory,
좋아, 이론적으로 꽤 많은 이야기를 했어,
but this would be a deep dive into real code
하지만 실제 코드에 대해 자세히 알아보겠습니다.
and how things look like in real life.
그리고 실제 생활에서 어떻게 보이는지.
So let me jump to our code and I'll spin up two services.
이제 코드로 넘어가서 두 개의 서비스를 실행해 보겠습니다.
So I'm spinning up a service called yarn, called items
그래서 저는 yarn이라는 서비스와 items라는 서비스를 스핀업합니다.
and another one is called users.
그리고 다른 하나는 사용자라고 합니다.
And I am going to send two types of API call.
그리고 두 가지 유형의 API 호출을 보내겠습니다.
I'm going to send slash data and that would return some data.
슬래시 데이터를 보내면 몇 가지 데이터를 반환할 것입니다.
And I would also, you know what, let's leave it with that.
그리고 이것도 그냥 놔두겠습니다.
So I sent one API call and when I'm sending
그래서 API 호출을 한 번 보냈는데
a single API call, now I want to visualize those traces.
이제 그 추적을 시각화하고 싶습니다.
So let's look at that, search for it
그럼 이걸 살펴보고 검색해 봅시다.
and we can see a very, very beautiful trace.
아주 아름다운 흔적을 볼 수 있습니다.
So that's what I would experience if I'm having an issue
문제가 발생하면 이런 현상이 나타납니다.
with this API call I'm trying to debug it.
이 API 호출로 디버깅을 시도하고 있습니다.
That's how a trace look like.
트레이스는 이렇게 생깁니다.
So that's just to give you a bit of a context,
약간의 맥락을 알려드리기 위한 것입니다,
let's jump to the code so you will see
코드로 이동하여 다음을 볼 수 있습니다.
what the code looks like.
코드가 어떻게 생겼는지 보시죠.
And I'll go briefly from the application layer code.
애플리케이션 레이어 코드를 간략히 살펴보겠습니다.
After that, I'll look at the application layer code.
그 다음에는 애플리케이션 레이어 코드를 살펴보겠습니다.
I'll show you a bit how Yeager and Prometheus,
예거와 프로메테우스가 어떻게 작동하는지 조금 보여드리겠습니다,
that's what I'm going to use in order to show you
를 보여드리기 위해 사용하겠습니다.
how much API calls we got.
얼마나 많은 API 호출을 받았는지 보여줍니다.
And then I'll look how the implementation
그리고 구현이 어떻게 되는지 살펴보겠습니다.
of open telemetry works.
어떻게 작동하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
I will say one thing, in this first session,
이 첫 번째 세션에서 한 가지 말씀드리겠습니다,
we're not going to deep dive into open telemetry a lot.
오픈 텔레메트리에 대해서는 깊이 있게 다루지 않을 것입니다.
That's what happened in the second session.
이것이 두 번째 세션에서 일어난 일입니다.
Okay, so let's look at item service.
이제 아이템 서비스를 살펴봅시다.
So this is by the way, Node.js with TypeScript.
참고로, 이것은 타입스크립트가 있는 Node.js입니다.
You don't need to understand Node.js and TypeScript
Node.js와 TypeScript를 이해할 필요는 없습니다.
in order to understand open telemetry,
오픈 텔레메트리를 이해하기 위해,
just the programming language that I use.
제가 사용하는 프로그래밍 언어만요.
So let me enlarge it a bit so it will be easier
조금 더 쉽게 볼 수 있도록 확대해서 보여드리겠습니다.
for you to see.
보실 수 있게요.
So the first thing that we do
그래서 우리가 가장 먼저 하는 일은
is we initialize open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리를 초기화합니다.
All you need to do in order to have open telemetry,
오픈 텔레메트리를 사용하기 위해 필요한 모든 작업입니다,
at least the basics of it,
최소한 기본적인 것들은,
is to initialize, import some file and then initialize it.
초기화하고, 파일을 가져온 다음 초기화하는 것입니다.
The file itself is not that long.
파일 자체는 그리 길지 않습니다.
So it's 42 lines of code with spaces.
공백을 포함한 42줄의 코드입니다.
So, and here we have one extra.
여기에 한 줄이 더 있습니다.
So it's fairly simple implementation.
아주 간단한 구현입니다.
We will dive into it in a second.
잠시 후에 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
And what we are doing is we are creating
그리고 우리가 하는 일은
an express application, which is a RESTful service.
레스트풀 서비스인 익스프레스 애플리케이션을 생성하는 것입니다.
And we are listening to sledge data,
그리고 우리는 슬레지 데이터를 수신하고 있습니다,
as you saw earlier, in the browser.
브라우저에서 보셨듯이요.
And basically, if we didn't get a fail in our query string,
기본적으로 쿼리 문자열에서 실패가 발생하지 않았다면,
what we're doing is we're calling the user service.
우리가 하는 일은 사용자 서비스를 호출하는 것입니다.
And if that's successful,
성공하면
we're just returning the user service data.
사용자 서비스 데이터를 반환합니다.
And if it's not successful,
성공하지 못하면
we are putting some error logs
몇 가지 오류 로그를 기록합니다.
to get all the data that we need.
필요한 모든 데이터를 가져옵니다.
And also, for every API call,
또한 모든 API 호출에 대해
we are adding one to our counter.
를 카운터에 추가합니다.
And this would be the HTTP calls counter
그리고 이것은 HTTP 호출 카운터입니다.
that we got from our HTTP call.
HTTP 호출에서 얻은 값입니다.
So you can see here a very quick view
매우 빠른 보기를 볼 수 있습니다.
of how we are working with metrics.
메트릭으로 작업하는 방식을 확인할 수 있습니다.
Cool, the user service is also a very simple service.
멋지네요, 사용자 서비스도 아주 간단한 서비스네요.
The same goes in import tracer,
임포트 트레이서도 마찬가지입니다,
initialize some express stuff.
몇 가지 표현식을 초기화합니다.
So we will have a REST service.
이제 REST 서비스가 생겼습니다.
And when we get a request to slash user,
그리고 사용자 슬래시 요청을 받으면,
we are using this mock API that I did.
제가 만든 이 모의 API를 사용하고 있습니다.
We get some users, some mock data user.
일부 사용자, 일부 모의 데이터 사용자를 얻습니다.
We randomize some index.
일부 인덱스를 무작위로 추출합니다.
We save what we randomize, and then we are just responding.
무작위로 추출한 것을 저장하고 응답만 합니다.
So basically, if I'll go back to our UI here,
기본적으로 여기 UI로 돌아가 보겠습니다,
to our UI go browser, what you can see here,
로 이동하면 다음과 같이 표시됩니다,
you can see that we sent an API call to item service,
아이템 서비스에 API 호출을 보낸 것을 확인할 수 있습니다,
item service communicated with user service,
아이템 서비스가 사용자 서비스와 통신했습니다,
and everybody's happy.
모두가 행복합니다.
To give you an example of how it really looks.
실제 모습을 예로 들어보겠습니다.
So again, if I'm looking at the trace itself,
다시 트레이스 자체를 보면,
what I can see here,
여기서 볼 수 있는 것은
I can see that item service got an API call to slash data.
아이템 서비스가 데이터를 삭감하는 API 호출을 받은 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So I can see everything right here.
바로 여기서 모든 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
I can also see that it sent an API call to slash users,
또한 사용자 삭감을 위한 API 호출을 보낸 것도 볼 수 있습니다,
as we saw in the code.
코드에서 보았듯이.
And now I can also see that we communicated
그리고 이제 우리가 다음과 같이 통신한 것도 볼 수 있습니다.
with the mock EIO and we got the data that we wanted to.
모의 EIO와 통신하여 원하는 데이터를 얻었습니다.
And we can see how long everything took.
그리고 모든 과정이 얼마나 오래 걸렸는지 확인할 수 있습니다.
We can see that nothing works in parallel.
병렬로 작동하는 것은 없다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
Everything is in sequence and it's quite fast thing.
모든 것이 순서대로 진행되며 매우 빠릅니다.
By the way, if I would ask you a question
그건 그렇고, 하나만 물어볼게요.
on this particular trace,
이 특정 추적에서,
if I want to improve this trace in terms of performance,
이 트레이스를 성능 측면에서 개선하고 싶습니다,
what do I need to improve?
무엇을 개선해야 하나요?
What is the thing that makes my life,
내 삶을 만드는 것은 무엇인가요?
not my life, the customer life,
내 삶이 아니라 고객의 삶입니다,
wait the most time?
가장 오래 기다린 시간?
So usually you need to, with traces,
그래서 보통은 흔적을 남겨야 합니다,
you need to work your way up.
위로 올라가야 합니다.
So this thing takes a long time.
시간이 오래 걸리네요.
This is the call to our mock UI.
모의 UI에 대한 호출입니다.
And this is the thing that blocks most of my IO.
그리고 이것이 제 IO의 대부분을 차단하는 것입니다.
So basically if I were able to improve it,
그래서 기본적으로 제가 개선할 수 있다면,
the whole trace would improve again,
전체 추적이 다시 개선될 것입니다,
from performance and latency aspect.
성능과 지연 시간 측면에서 개선되었습니다.
Okay.
오케이.
So we got a bit of a sense of how this thing looks like.
이제 이게 어떻게 생겼는지 어느 정도 감이 오네요.
Oh, I do want to show you what happens
오, 무슨 일이 일어나는지 보여드리고 싶네요.
when I'm adding an error.
오류를 추가할 때
So I have fail and fail one.
그래서 나는 실패하고 실패했습니다.
So now I got internal server error.
이제 내부 서버 오류가 발생했습니다.
And if I go and search again on Yeager
그리고 예거에서 다시 검색하면
to find the trace that I failed,
실패한 흔적을 찾을 수 없습니다,
I can see here that there wasn't a call to user service.
여기에서 사용자 서비스에 대한 호출이 없었음을 알 수 있습니다.
And I do have error true.
그리고 에러가 참입니다.
And I can also see the error details right here.
오류 세부 정보도 바로 여기에 표시됩니다.
And if I'll go to Prometheus,
그리고 프로메테우스로 가볼게요,
I can see that the count of API call is increasing
API 호출 횟수가 증가하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
because we are counting on API calls
API 호출을 계산하고 있기 때문입니다.
and we're getting more and more.
그리고 점점 더 많아지고 있습니다.
Okay.
So now that we have a bit of an understanding
이제 어느 정도 이해가 되셨을 겁니다.
of what the application is doing
애플리케이션이 무엇을 하고 있는지
and how our monitoring tools are working,
모니터링 도구가 어떻게 작동하는지
let's dive one step inside how this thing is working.
어떻게 작동하는지 한 걸음 더 들어가 보겠습니다.
And let's take a look at the tracer.
추적기를 살펴봅시다.
Again, just to emphasize,
다시 한 번 강조합니다,
this is not a deep dive into open telemetry.
이것은 오픈 텔레메트리에 대한 심층 분석이 아닙니다.
There is a lot of setup,
설정이 많습니다,
there is a lot of moving components in the SDK,
SDK에 움직이는 컴포넌트가 많이 있습니다,
different names that you may see like provider,
공급자처럼 다른 이름이 표시될 수 있습니다,
like exported that we need to really understand
우리가 정말로 이해해야 할 exported와 같은
and deep dive into them.
그리고 깊이 파고들어야 합니다.
But I do want to give you a sense of how this thing works.
하지만 이게 어떻게 작동하는지는 알려드리고 싶네요.
So next time we'll be able to dive right into it.
그럼 다음번에는 더 자세히 알아볼 수 있을 거야.
So next session, I will just assume
그럼 다음 세션에서는
that you already saw this code
이 코드를 이미 봤다고 가정합니다.
and we are going to extend it
그리고 우리는 그것을 확장할 것입니다
and have more and more understanding
그리고 점점 더 많은 것을 이해하게 됩니다.
on what is the provider and exported
공급자와 내보낸 것에 대해
and processor and all those kinds of things.
그리고 프로세서와 그런 모든 종류의 것들.
So the first thing that is happening here
여기서 가장 먼저 일어나는 일은
is we are setting up our metric configuration.
메트릭 구성을 설정하고 있습니다.
And when you say metric,
그리고 메트릭이라고 하면
you need to send this metric somewhere
이 메트릭을 어딘가로 보내야 합니다.
and I'm going to use metric Prometheus exporter.
메트릭 Prometheus 내보내기를 사용하겠습니다.
That means that our metrics
즉, 메트릭
are going to be shipped to Prometheus.
가 프로메테우스로 전송될 것입니다.
And I'm using here some metric port that I'm defining.
그리고 여기에 제가 정의한 메트릭 포트를 사용하고 있습니다.
So if you look in the user service,
그래서 사용자 서비스를 보면
I am providing here a port for scraping
여기에 스크래핑을 위한 포트를 제공하고 있습니다.
and the item service has a different port
그리고 항목 서비스에는 다른 포트가 있습니다.
for scraping the metrics.
로 변경합니다.
So in case you don't know the way Prometheus works
Prometheus의 작동 방식을 모르시는 분들을 위해 다음과 같이 설명합니다.
is Prometheus scrape the data from the service.
는 프로메테우스가 서비스에서 데이터를 스크랩하는 것입니다.
So you need to expose some API call,
따라서 일부 API 호출을 노출해야 합니다,
some API endpoint that Prometheus can fetch the data from
Prometheus가 데이터를 가져올 수 있는 일부 API 엔드포인트를 노출해야 합니다.
to show you how it looks.
어떻게 보이는지 보여드리겠습니다.
So the URL, the port was 8081 and slash metrics
따라서 URL, 포트는 8081이고 슬래시 메트릭은 다음과 같습니다.
and this is how Prometheus works.
이것이 프로메테우스가 작동하는 방식입니다.
They're sending an API call to slash metrics
메트릭을 줄이기 위해 API 호출을 보내고 있습니다.
and that's the way that they are getting the metrics from.
그리고 이것이 그들이 메트릭을 가져오는 방식입니다.
By the way, if I look in Yeager
그건 그렇고, 예거에서 보면
and you can see here that we have here our arrow
여기에 화살표가 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
but we have also bunch of very short, very small,
하지만 아주 짧고 아주 작은 화살표도 있습니다,
very short, very small traces.
아주 짧고 아주 작은 흔적들이 있습니다.
And if you look at those traces,
그리고 그 흔적들을 보면
those traces would be the traces for slash metric.
이 트레이스는 슬래시 메트릭의 트레이스입니다.
So the API calls that Prometheus is sending
따라서 Prometheus가 전송하는 API 호출은 다음과 같습니다.
in order to fetch the metrics are visible
메트릭을 가져오기 위해 전송하는 API 호출은 다음과 같습니다.
also right here in Yeager.
여기 예거에서도 마찬가지입니다.
Cool, so we defined that once it's up and running,
멋지네요, 일단 실행하면 이렇게 정의했습니다,
we are writing in the logger that the data,
로거에 데이터를 기록합니다,
what is the address of the scraper?
스크레이퍼의 주소는 무엇인가요?
So you can see here the scraper and the address
여기에서 스크레이퍼와 주소를 볼 수 있습니다.
and then we're asking to fetch the traces every second.
그리고 매초마다 트레이스를 가져오도록 요청하고 있습니다.
Probably in production I would use less
아마 프로덕션에서는 더 적게 사용할 것입니다.
but this is a demo and I want things to be up to update fresh.
하지만 이것은 데모이고 나는 모든 것이 새로 업데이트되기를 원합니다.
After that, we need to define the traces
그런 다음 트레이스를 정의해야 합니다.
and traces are being exported to Yeager.
트레이스가 예거로 내보내지고 있습니다.
We are specifying the name of the service,
서비스 이름을 지정하고 있습니다,
the user service and the item service
사용자 서비스 및 아이템 서비스
and then we are asking to instrument HTTP and express
그리고 나서 HTTP와 express를 계측하도록 요청합니다.
in order for us to go see the data that is incoming
들어오는 데이터를 확인하기 위해
to express via the REST API and also the outgoing API calls
REST API와 나가는 API 호출을 통해 표현할 수 있습니다.
that are being sent from item service to user service
항목 서비스에서 사용자 서비스로 전송되는 호출
and from user service to demo.
그리고 사용자 서비스에서 데모로
Cool, looking at our item service,
좋아요, 아이템 서비스를 살펴보세요,
so there isn't a lot of API,
그래서 API가 많지 않아요,
an open telemetry API here.
여기에 오픈 텔레메트리 API가 있습니다.
So there are two things that we're doing
그래서 우리가 하는 일은 두 가지입니다.
with open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리로.
So if everything works correctly
모든 것이 올바르게 작동한다면
and we don't have any failure
실패가 없다면
and we're looking at the code that is being executed,
실행 중인 코드를 살펴봅니다,
so we are in the slash get, it's not failing,
따라서 우리는 슬래시 겟에 있고, 실패하지 않습니다,
we are sending in a response and that is it.
응답을 보내고 있습니다.
So you barely, you don't see any open telemetry data here
여기에는 열려 있는 텔레메트리 데이터가 거의 보이지 않습니다.
and this is because everything works fine
모든 것이 정상적으로 작동하기 때문입니다.
and we don't need to do anything special
그리고 우리는 특별한 일을 할 필요가 없습니다.
so the trace would look as follows.
따라서 추적은 다음과 같이 보일 것입니다.
But when things are failing and we're having an exception,
하지만 문제가 발생하여 예외가 발생했습니다,
this is where things are starting
여기서 문제가 시작됩니다.
to get a bit more complicated.
조금 더 복잡해집니다.
So I wanted to be able to correlate
그래서 저는 상관관계를 파악하고 싶었습니다.
between my logs and my traces.
내 로그와 내 흔적 사이.
To do that, I am writing a log.
이를 위해 로그를 작성하고 있습니다.
So when I have an exception, I'm writing the console error,
그래서 예외가 발생하면 콘솔 오류를 기록하고 있습니다,
meaning that I have some failure
이는 내가 어떤 실패가 있다는 것을 의미합니다.
and you can see this failure right here.
바로 여기서 이 실패를 볼 수 있습니다.
If I would output from my application critical error,
내 애플리케이션에서 치명적인 오류를 출력하면
I won't be able to know what is a trace.
트레이스가 무엇인지 알 수 없습니다.
So for every log that I'm writing,
그래서 내가 쓰는 모든 로그에 대해,
I am attaching the trace ID
추적 ID를 첨부합니다.
and this is what you can see right here.
바로 여기에 이렇게 표시됩니다.
So basically I'm going to the open telemetry API,
기본적으로 오픈 텔레메트리 API로 이동합니다,
that's the open telemetry API
오픈 텔레메트리 API입니다.
and I'm asking from the open telemetry API
오픈 텔레메트리 API에서 요청합니다.
to give me the current spec, the active spec.
현재 사양, 즉 활성 사양을 알려달라고 요청합니다.
Remember every line here is a spec
여기 모든 줄이 사양임을 기억하세요.
and this is happening in the item service
그리고 이것은 아이템 서비스에서 일어나고 있습니다.
and this is happening in the user service,
사용자 서비스에서 발생하고 있습니다,
so we have space that are currently active.
따라서 현재 활성화된 공간이 있습니다.
Once I got the active span,
활성 스팬을 얻었으니
I can write with my log that I have,
내가 가지고 있는 로그로 쓸 수 있습니다,
what is the current trace ID?
현재 추적 ID는 무엇인가요?
So imagine next time you have production issue,
다음에 프로덕션 문제가 발생한다고 가정해 보세요,
you have an exception in your logs.
로그에 예외가 발생합니다.
In your log, you have the relevant trace ID
로그에 관련 추적 ID가 있습니다.
and you can take this trace ID right here
이 추적 ID를 바로 여기에서 가져올 수 있습니다.
and you can grab it and search by the trace ID
추적 ID로 검색할 수 있습니다.
and I got the trace ID that is causing all of my issues.
그리고 모든 문제의 원인이 되는 추적 ID를 찾았습니다.
So the ability to jump between a trace
따라서 트레이스 사이를 이동하는 기능은
and a log between a log and a trace
로그와 트레이스 사이를 이동할 수 있습니다.
is very simple and very, very fast.
는 매우 간단하고 매우 빠릅니다.
Also I did here implementation of metrics.
또한 여기서 메트릭을 구현했습니다.
I kind of show you it already.
이미 보여드렸습니다.
We'll talk about metrics of course with great more details
물론 메트릭에 대해 더 자세히 이야기하겠습니다.
but essentially you create a meter,
하지만 기본적으로 미터를 만드는 것입니다,
you create a counter, you provide it with a name,
카운터를 생성하고 이름을 지정합니다,
you need to increase and decrease it
카운터를 늘리거나 줄여야 합니다.
and every time that you have an API call,
그리고 API 호출이 있을 때마다,
this is running any time that you have an API call,
API 호출이 있을 때마다 실행됩니다,
it's kind of a middleware,
일종의 미들웨어입니다,
it eventually would end up in Prometheus
결국 프로메테우스에 들어가게 될 것이다.
and you can see here the amount of calls that we're getting
그리고 여기에서 우리가 받고 있는 호출의 양을 볼 수 있습니다.
and you can kind of track it from there.
거기서부터 추적할 수 있습니다.
When the API call is being sent to the user service
API 호출이 사용자 서비스로 전송되는 경우
and this is happening right here,
바로 여기서 일어나고 있습니다,
I didn't need to do anything special with open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리로 특별한 작업을 할 필요가 없었습니다.
I needed to do, I didn't need to write some code
코드를 작성할 필요가 없었습니다.
in order to be able to see both in the user service
사용자 서비스에서 두 가지를 모두 볼 수 있도록 하기 위해
and the item service, that's happened automatically.
그리고 아이템 서비스에서 자동으로 발생했습니다.
Of course, something that we will learn how to do
물론, 어떻게 해야 하는지 배우게 될 것입니다.
and in the user service, I did something a bit,
그리고 사용자 서비스에서 뭔가를 좀 했어요,
which I think it's interesting and important.
흥미롭고 중요하다고 생각합니다.
So if everything works and I'm refreshing here,
그래서 모든 것이 작동하고 내가 여기서 상쾌하다면,
so you can see that I'm getting Harry Potter
내가 해리 포터를 얻는다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
and getting different names.
그리고 다른 이름을 얻습니다.
So it's kind of a random thing, right?
일종의 무작위 현상이죠?
Because I did call random number
난수를 호출했으니까
of zero to the length of the array
배열의 길이에 0을 곱한 값
and if I look at the trace,
그리고 트레이스를 보면
and let's jump to the trace,
트레이스로 이동해 보겠습니다,
let's find the latest traces, find this one.
가장 최근의 흔적을 찾아보자, 이걸 찾아보자.
So I have no idea why user service chose
그래서 왜 사용자 서비스가
to return this user.
을 선택했는지 모르겠습니다.
It's completely random, right?
완전히 무작위죠?
So I'm not sure if you'll be able to see it,
그래서 네가 볼 수 있을지 모르겠다,
but if in the right corner of the screen,
하지만 화면 오른쪽 구석에 있다면요,
there is a small pipe and it describes
작은 파이프가 있고
that there was some log.
로그가 있다고 설명합니다.
So I was able to write log within my tricks.
그래서 저는 제 트릭 안에 로그를 쓸 수 있었습니다.
And this log is saying, hey, a number was random
그리고 이 로그는 숫자가 무작위였다고 말하고 있습니다.
and the random number that was generated is one.
그리고 생성된 난수는 1입니다.
So if I'm a developer and I need to figure out
만약 제가 개발자이고 다음과 같은 경우
why this user was returned, it seems so random,
왜 이 사용자가 반환되었는지 알아내야 한다면 너무 무작위로 보입니다,
now I have my answer because I know
이제 답을 알았으니
that it was index number one that was generated.
생성된 인덱스가 1번 인덱스임을 알 수 있습니다.
And again, I'm getting an API call.
그리고 다시 API 호출을 받습니다.
I'm grabbing the active span and in the active span,
활성 스팬과 활성 스팬에 있습니다,
I am adding a new event.
새 이벤트를 추가하고 있습니다.
An event can have a name, well, it must have a name
이벤트는 이름을 가질 수 있습니다, 이름이 있어야 합니다.
and also it can send how many data that you want.
그리고 원하는 만큼의 데이터를 전송할 수도 있습니다.
So you can treat it as just more info being sent
따라서 더 많은 정보가 전송되는 것으로 간주할 수 있습니다.
on the span and then the trace.
스팬과 추적에 대한 정보입니다.
And you can also treat it as the real exception,
그리고 이것을 실제 예외로 취급할 수도 있습니다,
the real exception to real data that we got.
실제 데이터에 대한 실제 예외로 취급할 수도 있습니다.
And this is like extremely helpful
그리고 이것은 매우 유용합니다.
because it gives you the opportunity to get everything
모든 것을 얻을 수 있는 기회를 주니까요
that you want in the story.
이야기에서 원하는 것을 얻을 수 있기 때문입니다.
Michael, we actually have a question from the audience
마이클, 청중의 질문이 있습니다.
related to what you touched earlier regarding metrics.
아까 메트릭에 관해 말씀하신 것과 관련된 질문입니다.
Is there a way to filter out metric calls
메트릭 호출을 필터링할 수 있는 방법이 있나요?
from the traces list?
추적 목록에서 필터링할 수 있나요?
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
네, 네, 맞아요.
It's a great question because, well,
좋은 질문이네요,
you don't care about this slash metric.
이 슬래시 메트릭을 신경쓰지 않으니까요.
Although it's cool that it's there,
그래도 거기 있는 건 멋지네요,
you don't really care about it.
당신은 그것에 대해 별로 신경 쓰지 않아요.
So yeah, it's up to you to decide what's being instrumented
그래요, 무엇을 계측할지는 당신에게 달렸어요.
and what's not.
그리고 무엇이 아닌지.
This is something that we will learn exactly how to do
이것은 우리가 정확히 어떻게 해야 하는지 배울 것입니다.
when we will work more in depth into open telemetry.
개방형 원격 측정에 대해 더 깊이 연구할 때입니다.
Basically the processor phase is the phase
기본적으로 프로세서 단계는
where you can decide that you're going to omit some traces
일부 흔적을 생략하기로 결정할 수 있습니다.
because they are slash metric.
슬래시 메트릭이기 때문입니다.
Other types of things that you would probably want to omit
생략하고 싶은 다른 유형의 것들
is stuff like maybe health checks
건강 검진 같은 것들
that could be very annoying or some bots
매우 성가시거나 일부 봇일 수 있습니다.
that are kind of annoying your application.
애플리케이션을 성가시게 하는 봇입니다.
Cool, thank you.
좋아요, 고마워요.
One thing that I wanted to show you guys
너희들에게 보여주고 싶은 게 있어
before closing this session,
이 세션을 닫기 전에
you can see when we have error,
오류가 발생하면 확인할 수 있습니다,
I'm taking the active span,
활성 스팬을 가져옵니다,
I'm writing to our log the trace ID
로그에 추적 ID를 기록 중입니다.
and then also be calling the exception.
그리고 예외를 호출합니다.
That reason is for when we have a failure,
그 이유는 장애가 발생했을 때를 위한 것입니다,
let me make it crash.
충돌하게 해줘요.
When we have a failure and I am able to see
장애가 발생하고 내가 볼 수 있을 때
that I had error right here,
바로 여기에 오류가 있음을 알 수 있습니다,
that's great, that's cool,
잘됐네, 잘됐어,
but I do want to know exactly what was the error.
하지만 정확히 무엇이 오류인지 알고 싶습니다.
So I can see here that the event type is exception,
여기서 이벤트 유형이 예외임을 알 수 있습니다,
the event message is a really bad error
이벤트 메시지는 정말 나쁜 오류입니다.
and here I can see the stack trace
그리고 여기에 스택 추적을 볼 수 있습니다.
so I'll be able to debug it and to fix it.
디버깅하고 수정할 수 있습니다.
Okay, so our goal for today was for this live session,
자, 오늘의 목표는 이 라이브 세션입니다,
it was to send traces to Jaeger and view some logs.
예거에게 트레이스를 전송하고 로그를 확인하는 것이었습니다.
We got that done.
해냈어요.
To send metrics to Prometheus, we got that done.
메트릭을 Prometheus로 전송하는 작업을 완료했습니다.
We were able to collect trace,
추적을 수집할 수 있었습니다,
to correlate traces and logs, we have that working.
추적과 로그의 상관관계를 파악할 수 있었습니다.
And if you're interested in that code,
그리고 이 코드에 관심이 있으시다면,
you have everything in our repository,
저장소에 모든 것이 있습니다,
just go to aspect.bed-io, openMP bootcamp.
aspect.bed-io, openMP 부트캠프로 이동하세요.
You'll have link to the video recording
비디오 녹화 링크가 표시됩니다.
that is being recorded right now,
지금 녹화 중입니다,
the slides, the Slack channel
슬라이드, 슬랙 채널
and of course the source code itself.
그리고 물론 소스 코드 자체도요.
In the next section, we're going to implement
다음 섹션에서는 다음과 같이 구현하겠습니다.
everything that we did here, but with more details.
여기서 한 모든 것을 더 자세히 설명합니다.
And I think the question that we got to remove slash metric
그리고 슬래시 메트릭을 제거해야 할 것 같습니다.
is exactly the kind of thing that we are going to do
이 바로 우리가 할 일입니다.
because we are looking for real life issues
우리는 실제 문제를 찾고 있기 때문입니다.
we faced when we work with open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리로 작업할 때 직면한 문제입니다.
Yeah, so we have to get your questions.
네, 질문이 있으신가요?
Cool, yeah, so we already have a first question,
좋아요, 벌써 첫 번째 질문이 나왔네요,
like a general question about open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리에 대한 일반적인 질문 같은 거요
and open telemetry compares
개방형 텔레메트리 비교
to regular application monitoring APMs,
를 일반 애플리케이션 모니터링 APM과 비교합니다,
like AppDynamics and Dynatrace.
앱다이나믹스 및 다이나트레이스와 같이.
What is the real difference?
실제 차이점은 무엇인가요?
Is it just about how logs and metrics correlated
로그와 메트릭의 상관 관계에 관한 것일까요?
or is there anything else here?
아니면 다른 이유가 있나요?
Yeah, great question.
네, 좋은 질문입니다.
So open telemetry by itself is the method to collect data
그러니까 오픈 텔레메트리는 그 자체로 데이터를 수집하는 방법입니다.
and to distribute it.
배포하는 방법입니다.
So it's not about what you do with this data.
따라서 이 데이터로 무엇을 하느냐가 중요한 게 아닙니다.
You do have the area to visualize the data,
데이터를 시각화할 수 있는 영역이 있습니다,
but that's the tip of the iceberg, right?
하지만 이건 빙산의 일각이죠?
You just can see the trace.
흔적만 보이네요.
Companies like Dynatrace and AppDynamics
다이나트레이스와 앱다이나믹스 같은 회사들
are companies that basically trying to solve the problem
기본적으로 문제를 해결하려고 노력하는 기업들입니다.
that open telemetry collects data to solve,
오픈 텔레메트리로 데이터를 수집하여 문제를 해결하려는 기업입니다,
which is to fix issues faster.
문제를 더 빨리 해결하기 위한 것입니다.
Both companies used to not work with open telemetry
두 회사 모두 개방형 텔레메트리를 사용하지 않았습니다.
and migrating to open telemetry.
개방형 텔레메트리로 마이그레이션합니다.
So any APM tool that you know out there
따라서 여러분이 알고 있는 모든 APM 도구는
is doing some extent of effort to migrate to open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리로 마이그레이션하기 위해 어느 정도 노력하고 있습니다.
I think the question from the consumer side is,
소비자 측의 질문은 다음과 같습니다,
I want to be part of the community.
커뮤니티의 일원이 되고 싶어요.
I want to be part of the standard
표준의 일부가 되고 싶습니다.
and I want to get the flexibility that I want to have
나는 내가 원하는 유연성을 얻고 싶다.
when I'm working with the standard.
표준으로 작업할 때.
That means that you will be able to collect
즉, 다음을 수집할 수 있습니다.
open telemetry data and then ship it whenever you want.
텔레메트리 데이터를 열어 원할 때마다 전송할 수 있습니다.
You will be able to ship it to your favorite APM tool,
선호하는 APM 도구로 전송할 수 있습니다,
but also you may be able to part of it
하지만 일부만 전송할 수도 있습니다.
versus for yourself or other purposes.
대 자신이나 다른 목적을 위해.
Or if you want to, let's say,
또는 원할 경우,
ship traces to one vendor because he's very,
한 공급업체로 배송 추적을 보냅니다,
very good with traces and then the metrics
추적과 메트릭에 매우 능숙합니다.
and the logs to another one, because it's good at that,
그리고 로그를 다른 것으로 옮겼습니다,
it will give you this flexibility.
이 유연성을 제공합니다.
But in a sense, open telemetry is going to change a bit
하지만 어떤 의미에서 개방형 텔레메트리는 약간 바뀔 것입니다.
how we're using APM as for today.
오늘날 우리가 APM을 사용하는 방식이 달라질 것입니다.
So if in the past, like APMs,
그렇다면 과거에는 APM처럼
each one of them had its own proprietary capabilities
각각 고유한 기능을 가지고 있었습니다.
of how to collect the data, proprietary agents
데이터를 수집하는 방법, 독점 에이전트
and ways to deploy and collect data.
데이터를 배포하고 수집하는 방법
So to some extent,
어느 정도는요,
open telemetry is commoditizing the data layer.
개방형 텔레메트리가 데이터 계층을 상품화하고 있습니다.
And now it's more of a question of like,
이제는 '좋아요'의 문제입니다,
what are you doing with this data?
이 데이터로 뭘 할 건가요?
And probably each vendor has its own ways to do that.
아마도 각 벤더마다 고유한 방법이 있을 겁니다.
But maybe another interesting thing
하지만 또 다른 흥미로운 점은
that we will touch on later on in these sessions,
이 세션의 뒷부분에서 다룰 것입니다,
maybe more of the last ones are,
어쩌면 마지막에 더 많이 있을지도 모르죠,
what else we can do with this data?
이 데이터로 또 무엇을 할 수 있을까요?
Because it's not just about an alert in production,
단순히 프로덕션의 경보에 관한 것이 아니기 때문입니다,
it's actually a very, very powerful data layer
실제로는 매우 강력한 데이터 레이어입니다.
that can be used for different purposes.
다양한 용도로 사용할 수 있습니다.
Okay, cool.
좋아, 멋지네.
Maybe just a few last thing before we're closing.
닫기 전에 마지막으로 몇 가지만 더 할게요.
Please join our channel in the CNCF Slack
CNCF 슬랙의 채널에 참여해주세요.
Open Telemetry Bootcamp.
원격 측정 부트캠프를 엽니다.
If you've got any questions,
질문이 있으신가요?
feel free to ask them and I'll be happy to answer you.
언제든지 질문해 주시면 기꺼이 답변해 드리겠습니다.
Few more resources that you can find
더 많은 리소스를 찾을 수 있습니다.
mostly about how to run Eager locally
대부분 Eager를 로컬에서 실행하는 방법에 관한 것
and how to run Eager on AWS.
그리고 AWS에서 Eager를 실행하는 방법.
We're running on AWS,
AWS에서 실행 중입니다,
so that's why we chose to write about it.
그래서 이 글을 쓰기로 했습니다.
So if it's that interesting, you can definitely check it out.
그렇게 흥미롭다면 꼭 확인해보세요.
And as I said, next episode would be mostly about
그리고 말씀드렸듯이 다음 에피소드는 주로 다음과 같은 내용입니다.
integrating into our code.
우리 코드에 통합하는 것입니다.
Cool. All right, cool.
멋지네요. 좋아, 멋지다.
So yeah, Michael, thank you for that.
그래, 마이클, 고마워.
That was very interesting.
아주 재미있었어.
What is it? 53 minutes.
뭐지? 53분입니다.
Wow, that was really fast on my end.
와, 내가 보기엔 정말 빠르네.
So thank you very much for that.
정말 고마워요.
Thank you everybody that joined us.
함께 해주신 모든 분들께 감사드립니다.
As mentioned, this is gonna be available online
앞서 말씀드린 대로, 온라인으로도 시청하실 수 있습니다.
so you can access it whenever you want.
원할 때 언제든지 접속할 수 있습니다.
The Slack channel is available
슬랙 채널을 사용할 수 있습니다.
if you have questions outside of these sessions
이 세션 외에 질문이 있는 경우
or if there is anything in particular
또는 특별한 사항이 있는 경우
that you would like us to cover in future sessions.
다음 세션에서 다루었으면 하는 내용.
So be my guest and reach out.
언제든지 연락주세요.
We're here to promote Open Telemetry,
오픈 텔레메트리를 홍보하기 위해 왔습니다,
to promote the community, so feel free.
커뮤니티를 홍보하기 위해 왔으니 자유롭게 이용하세요.
So thank you again.
다시 한번 감사드립니다.
We'll be here in our next session.
다음 세션에서 뵙겠습니다.
Have a good rest of the day.
좋은 하루 되세요.
Bye-bye everybody.
모두 안녕히 계세요.
Bye-bye.
안녕.